<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The declaration and remonstrance of the lords, knights, and gentry of the countie of Cornwall. Agreed on by the whole county in generall, Oct. 10. 1642. VVherein is declared the resolution of the said lords, knights, and gentry, concerning the King and Parliament. Together with their proceedings against Sir Ralph Hopton, who hath now took castle in Cornwall, having there fifty peeces of ordnance, and 200 men. Together with the resolution of hoth Houses concerning the same.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A82055</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D547</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E122_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17964</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860315</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860315</idno>
            <idno type="VID">112434</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A82055)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 112434)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 21:E122[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The declaration and remonstrance of the lords, knights, and gentry of the countie of Cornwall. Agreed on by the whole county in generall, Oct. 10. 1642. VVherein is declared the resolution of the said lords, knights, and gentry, concerning the King and Parliament. Together with their proceedings against Sir Ralph Hopton, who hath now took castle in Cornwall, having there fifty peeces of ordnance, and 200 men. Together with the resolution of hoth Houses concerning the same.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Joseph Horton,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Octob. 13. 1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hopton, Ralph Hopton, --  Baron, 1598-1652.</term>
               <term>Cornwall  (England : County) --  History --  Sources --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Sources --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:112434:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE DECLARATION <hi>AND</hi> REMONSTRANCE OF THE Lords, Knights, and Gentry of the <hi>CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NTIE</hi> OF Cornwall.</p>
            <p>Agreed on by the whole County in generall, Octob. 10. 1642.</p>
            <p>VVherein is declared the Reſolution of the ſaid Lords, Knights, and Gentry, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the King and Parliament.</p>
            <p>Together with their proceedings againſt Sir <hi>Ralph Hopton,</hi> who hath now took Caſtle in <hi>Cornwall,</hi> having there fifty Peeces of Ordnance, and 200. men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Together with the Reſolution of hoth Houſes concerning the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Joſeph Horton.</hi> Octob. 13. 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:112434:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:112434:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE DECLARATION AND</hi> REMONSTRANCE of the <hi>Lords, Knights,</hi> and <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try</hi> of the Countie of <hi>CORNWALL,</hi> agreed on by the whole County in generall: <hi>Oct. 10<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 1642.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Right Honourable <hi>ROBERT</hi> Earle of <hi>Warwicke,</hi> having received intelligence from both Houſes of Parliament of the great preparations that are now making in Holland,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:112434:3"/>and to be ſent over into England to aſsiſt His Majeſty againſt the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Houſes of Parliament, he no ſooner had received their meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, but he ſent foure luſty brave Ships to guard the Sea Ports neere to New-Caſtle; And having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained there ſome certain time, by their Intelligencers abroad, they had information that five Ships lay hovering up and downe neere or about <hi>Calice,</hi> but they had no ſooner received this newes, but they preſently hoiſted ſaile, and tooke their way towards thoſe parts, but the enemy hearing of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, immediately ſtrooke ſaile and went towards <hi>Holland,</hi> inſomuch that before our Ships could get within ſight of them, they were
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:112434:3"/>gone; but it is very probable that the <hi>Hollanders</hi> will make ſtay of them there; the old Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> doth labour very much to ſend Arms &amp; ammunition to the King, but the young Prince is much againſt the ſame, and doth daily worke to turne his father from ſo doing.</p>
            <p>Information was given to the honourable Aſſembly of Parliament that Sir <hi>Ralph Hopton</hi> hath taken <hi>Pimick</hi> Caſtle in <hi>Cornwall,</hi> and hath ſtrongly fortified the ſame, having already about 200. ſouldiers in the ſame, and it was moreover ſignified that he hath got at the leaſt fifty pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Ordnance, and doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to ſhoote with the ſame daily, thinking by that means to make the County come in to aſſiſt him, but
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:112434:4"/>the greateſt part of the County ſtands firm and well affected to the Parliament, and are now reſolved to take the ſame reſolution as the men of <hi>Mancheſter</hi> did, having ſummo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the whole County to appeare within five miles of the ſaid Caſtle, and there to conclude on ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters that doth now concerne their liues and eſtates, and as it is ſuppoſed they will gather a head and beſiege the ſaid Caſtle: and for the aide and asſiſtance of them, the Parliament hath given order &amp; Command that thoſe two Regiments that are now going towards <hi>Briſtow</hi> and <hi>Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head,</hi> and ſhall goe into <hi>Cornwall</hi> to aid and asſiſt the COUNTIE and inhabitants againſt the ſaid Sir <hi>Ralph Hopton,</hi> and that the will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:112434:4"/>of both houſes ſhall bee made knowne therein; &amp; that their deſire is that more Forces ſhall be raiſed in that County to aid &amp; aſsiſt the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments Forces.</p>
            <p>There was alſo more letters came to the Houſe of COMMONS from <hi>Weſton Gate,</hi> intimating and ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying that the Marqueſs of <hi>Hartford</hi> is in South <hi>Wales,</hi> and doth daily labour and endeavour to win the hearts of the <hi>Welſhmen,</hi> ſtriving ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly to raiſe thoſe Counties to aid His Majeſty againſt the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, &amp; loſing very much of the great ſtrength he hath, ſaying that he is above 30000. ſtrong, Horſe and Foot.</p>
            <p>Thus he doth daily relate to thoſe parts, thinking by this meanes to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:112434:5"/>draw on thoſe that ſtand as New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, but it is credibly reported that His Majeſty hath not halfe that number.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prince</hi> Robert <hi>doth now begin to declare his Reſolution, concerning his reſidence here in</hi> England, <hi>and it is ſuppoſed that if His Majeſty would but give way to it, he would ſoone re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to</hi> Holland.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
